Charles Bowdoin Fillebrown Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Charles Bowdoin Fillebrown Papers 1879-1928 (bulk 1897-1917)
MSS85451
Fillebrown, Charles Bowdoin, 1842-1917
1,000 items
2 containers
.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Economist and author. Correspondence, speeches, and printed matter relating to Fillebrown's promotion of the single tax and the activities of the Massachusetts Single Tax League.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Carver, Thomas Nixon, 1865-1961--Correspondence.; Clark, John Bates, 1847-1938--Correspondence.; Commons, John R. (John Rogers), 1862-1945--Correspondence.; Ely, Richard T. (Richard Theodore), 1854-1943--Correspondence.; Fetter, Frank A. (Frank Albert), 1863-1949--Correspondence.; Fillebrown, Charles Bowdoin, 1842-1917.; Hirsch, Max, 1853-1909--Correspondence.; Johnson, Alvin Saunders, 1874-1971--Correspondence.; Nicholson, J. Shield (Joseph Shield), 1850-1927--Correspondence.; Plehn, Carl C. (Carl Copping), 1867- --Correspondence.; Seligman, Edwin R. A. (Edwin Robert Anderson), 1861-1939--Correspondence.; Taussig, F. W. (Frank William), 1859-1940--Correspondence.; Wright, Carroll D. (Carroll Davidson), 1840-1909--Correspondence.; Young, Allyn Abbott, 1876-1929--Correspondence.
Organizations
Massachusetts Single Tax League.
Subjects
Single tax.
Occupations
Authors.; Economists.
Provenance
The papers of Charles Bowdoin Fillebrown, economist and author, were given to the Library of Congress in 2009 by Sheldon Cohen.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Charles Bowdoin Fillebrown are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Charles Bowdoin Fillebrown (1842-1917) span the years 1879-1928 with the bulk of the material dating between 1897 and 1917. The correspondence relates chiefly to Fillebrown's promotion of the single tax concept. Correspondents include Thomas Nixon Carver, John Bates Clark, John R. Commons, Richard T. Ely, Frank A. Fetter, Max Hirsch, Alvin Saunders Johnson, J. Shield Nicholson, Carl C. Plehn, Edwin R. A. Seligman, F. W. Taussig, Carroll Davidson Wright, and Allyn Abbott Young. As part of his effort to build support for the single tax among mainstream academia, Fillebrown sent out a questionnaire on the subject to three hundred professors of political economy. The collection contains 165 responses. Also included are papers relating to the Massachusetts Single Tax League of which Fillebrown was president for many years. They consist chiefly of correspondence, speeches, and printed matter.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Incoming, 1886-1924 (Box 1)
    - A-R, (13 folders) (Box 1)
    - S-Y, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Outgoing, 1897-1912 (Box 2)
  - With Max Hirsch, 1902-1905 (Box 2)
- Massachusetts Single Tax League (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1879, 1897-1928 (Box 2)
  - Miscellany, 1897-1912 (Box 2)
  - Speeches and statements, 1899-1900 (Box 2)
- Questionnaire responses, 1901-1904, (4 folders) (Box 2)